Guide to the Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
184
Robertson family
.5 cubic ft.; 2 reels microfilm; 1 painting.
Letters, school records, painting.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence and other papers of the Robertson family of Washington County, New York, and several other related families. The papers of Smith Robertson consist of his letters written while a student at Union College (Schenectady, New York) and as superintendent of Common Schools in Tompkins County; also as a medical student at Geneva Medical College, at Yale University, and while traveling to Washington, D.C.; a painting by F. E. Robertson (brother of Mary "Grandma" Moses). Robertson family genealogy; also material on related families, including Bishop, Brown, Houtz, King, Snyder, Teeter, and Wood.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence and other papers of the Robertson family of Washington County, New York, and several other related families, dealing mostly with family matters and the migration westward of family members to Ohio, Missouri, Minnesota, and California. The papers of Smith Robertson consist of his letters written while a student at Union College (Schenectady, New York) and as superintendent of Common Schools in Tompkins County; also as a medical student at Geneva Medical College, at Yale University, and while traveling to Washington, D.C. Chief subjects include education, medicine, travel, and personal affairs. Correspondents include Horace Mann, Henry Barnard, and Douglass Boardman; he also describes meeting John Quincy Adams. Also, a painting by F. E. Robertson (brother of Mary "Grandma" Moses). Robertson family genealogy, including data on George Robertson (born in Scotland and lived in Dryden, New York); Smith Robertson, Hiram Robertson (husband of Mary Cornell); also material on related families, including Bishop, Brown, Houtz, King, Snyder, Teeter, and Wood.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Robertson family.; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848.; Barnard, Henry.; Bishop family.; Boardman, Douglass, 1822-1891.; Brown family.; Cornell, Mary.; Houtz family.; King family.; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859.; Moses, 1860-1961.; Robertson, F. E.; Robertson, Hiram.; Robertson, Smith.; Snyder family.; Teeter family.; Wood family.; Geneva Medical College (Geneva, N.Y.)--Students.; Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.)--Students.
Subjects:
Medical education--New York (State)--Geneva.; Teachers colleges--New York (State); Education--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Schools--Administration--New York (State)--Tompkins County.; Medicine--Study and teaching--New York (State)--Geneva.; Migration, Internal--Ohio.; Migration, Internal--Missouri.; Migration, Internal--Minnesota.; Migration, Internal--California.; Family--New York (State)--Washington County.
Places:
Washington County (N.Y.)--Genealogy.; Washington, D.C.--Description and travel.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes collections #184, #243, #908, and #852. Guide was originally created for collection #243
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Collection #243, Box 1: Folders 1-12
September 1840 - December 1841
January- October 1842
January 29 - October 7, 1843
January 9 - April 16, 1844
May 27 - December 31, 1844
January 10 - July 18, 1845
August 11 - November 13, 1845
January 27 - July 28, 1846
August 12 - October 26, 1846
February 19 - October 14, 1847
January 16, 1848 - June 30, 1852
Undated
Series II. Miscellaneous Letters and Receipts (not involving SR) 1821 - 1850
Collection #243, Box 1: Folder 13
Series III. Miscellaneous Madison and Chenango County School District Records
Collection #243, Box 1: Folder 14
CONTAINER LIST
- This Guide is Limited to the Contents of Former Collection #243
- Series I. Correspondence
  - September 1840 - December 1841 (10 items)
    - From Smith Robertson (SR) at Union College, Schenectady, to his parents, Mr. and Mrs. George Robertson, at Varna, September 5, 1840 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
      Concerned with the College. (SR member of July 1843 graduating class.)
    - SR, Union, from E. Canfield, Sandisfield, November 15, 1840 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
    - From W. Smith at Yale to SR at Union; is concerned with life at Yale; courses; death of a friend, November 29, 1840 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
    - From SR at Union to William H. Lacy at Cortland Academy, Homer, November (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
      "Seward runs behind while Bouck runs far ahead of his ticket"; other political comments. Also, references to college life, studies, professors.
    - From B. C. Whiting, Binghamton, to SR, March 15, 1841 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
    - From O. S. Wood, Dryden, to SR at Union, March 25, 1841 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
    - Printed report form from Union; addressed to George Robertson, April [6] 1841 (postmark) (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
      Includes tuition bill and marks for term January 8-April 1, 1841; also general information on courses, admission requirements, etc.
    - From Ruel Smith, Rochester, May 21, 1841 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
      Who is studying medicine in the office of a professor of surgery at Geneva Medical College; mentions practices of medical students who procured corpses already buried for their dissections. To SR at Union.
    - Term report from Union as in April above, August 11, 1841 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
      For period April 30-July 28, 1841.
    - From Cousin Molly, Albany, to SR at Union, December 9, 1841 (Box 243 1, Folder 1)
  - January- October 1842 (11 items)
    - From SR at Union College to William H. Lacy, Cortlandville, January 8 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
      Remarks about newly elected state legislators; plans for present term at College and future entering of Law School.
    - To SR at Union from N. B. Smith, Ithaca, February 21, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
    - Term report from Union for period January 7-April 1, 1842, April 9 (postmark) (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
    - From William Smith at Yale to SR at Union, May 12 or 13 (sic), 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
    - From Howard Townsend, Albany, to SR at Union, May 29, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
      Tells of H's journey to Washington, D.C.; his meeting John Quincy Adams, Daniel Webster, hearing Henry Clay speak, dining at the White House with President Tyler, and seeing the sights of the Capital.
    - From James Wood, Jr., Union College, to SR in Dryclen, July 8, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
      About an overpayment of a debt; SR now in a lawyer's office.
    - From Isaac Mott to SR at Union, July 12, 1842(postmark) (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
    - To SR from a cousin. Tells of the illness of his Aunt Sally, July 25, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
    - Term report from Union for period April 29th-July 27, 1842, August 10, 1842 (postmark) (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
    - From Cyrus Robertson in Albion, Michigan, to his brother, SR, September 5, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
      Concern about worth of Michigan land SR wishers to sell
    - From Walter Mott, cousin of SR, October 12, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 2)
      Invitation to SR to visit Mott in Albany at; the Medical College and perhaps see an operation performed.
  - January 29 - October 7, 1843 (9 items)
    - From Howard Townsend at Union to SR in Etna, January 29, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
    - From Mitchell (fraternity brother of SR?), "Ike" and others to SR, February 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
    - From N. R. Biddlecomb, and others to SR, March 31, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
      Urging his return to Union College and reporting events since his departure.
    - From State of New York, Secretary's Office, Department of Common Schools Albany to SR- -Superintendent of Common Schools, Tompkins Co., Ithaca, April 10, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
      Regarding a law of 1843 stating that all appeals presented to the State Secretary's Office must have first been submitted to and had a decision rendered by the superintendent of schools in the particular county.
    - From M. Scofield, Whitesboro, to SR, April 16, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
    - From SR at Union College to parents, May 1, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
      Regarding his return to College
    - From D. R. Houts, Ithaca, to SR at Union College, May 23, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
    - From Hiram D. Robertson at Albion, Michigan, to Parents (George Robertson) about trip to Detroit, May 23, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
    - From Asa Barton, Union College to SR at Varna, Tompkins Co, October 7, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 3)
      About news of SR's fraternity at Union, Sigma Phi.
  - January 9 - April 16, 1844 (11 items)
    - From W. Smith at Yale University to SR, Varna, Tompkins Co., N.Y, January 9, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Some facts about life at Yale and news of friends
    - From S. Town of Aurora to SR, January 18, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      About Town help including Robertson with a "pioneer enterprise thro' which the cause of primary education will receive so much aid."
    - From H. Gillam of Aurora to SR about the possible visit of a Mr. Town, February 15, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
    - From S. Town of Aurora to SR, February 27, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Says that a visit to Tompkins Co. would be impossible. Town speaks of a project undertaken by Tompkins Co. teachers that has spread to other parts of the State; he commends the venture and wishes them success in the future.
    - From A. Potter, Union College, to SR, Ithaca, March 6, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Potter isn't sure whether or not he will be able to attend an Institute.
    - From S. Young, Secretary's Office, Department of Common Schools, Albany to SR, Superintendent of Tompkins Co. Common Schools, March 11, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Regarding teacher certification for a Mr. Curtis and commending SR on the reputation of the Teachers' Institute
    - From D. A. Morton, town clerk, Groton, to SR, Superintendent Common Schools of Tompkins County, March 11, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Listing names of district clerks for the Groton Common Schools.
    - From Eleaser Carter of Caroline, to SR, March 20, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Informing SR that the trustees have refused his (SR's) request for a meeting. Carter says that he will arrange for SR to review the clerk's books and will give SR all the help that he can.
    - From Cyrus Clark and John S. Holden to SR as Superintendent of Tompkins Co. Common Schools, March 21, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      A notice of an appeal being sent to the N.Y.S. Superintendent of Schools concerning the Board of Trustees' refusal to comply with an existing statute. SR. had ruled in favor of the Trustees.
    - George B. Glendening, Cayuga Academy, Aurora to SR, March 27, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Acceptance of invitation to visit SR.
    - From S. Young, State of New York Secretary's Office, Dept of Common. Schools, to SR, March 30, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      State Superintendent upholds decision of SR in the case of Holden and Clark vs. the Trustees of the town, of Lansing District #7, saying that trustees have right to levy tax.
    - From Douglass Boardman, Trumansburg, to SR, April 3, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Letter tells of the electioneering done by Boardman's opponents in an election in the attempts to get another man elected.
    - From S. Town, Angelica, to SR, April 16, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 4)
      Reports on the Teacher's Institute in Angelica.
  - May 27 - December 31, 1844 (14 items)
    - To SR from. S.D. Carr of Groton, May 27, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      A man in the school district refuses to pay taxes on land which is not in said district.
    - From Douglass Boardman, Trumansburg, to SR, June 4, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Requesting that SR send the dates he will be able to visit Trumansburg.
    - Printed invitation from Alpha of the Sigma Phi with note from How(ard?) Porter, June 29, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
    - To SR from S. D. Carr, July 29, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Asking that SR visit the Groton district schools and commenting on the next school term.
    - From Lyman Cobb, N.Y.C. to SR, August 12, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      About text books being considered by the Books Committee of the County School Association.
    - From S. Young, Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, Albany, to SR, August 13, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Granting the request for an extension in handing in the district's annual report and commending the evaluation SR is doing of the Common Schools in Tompkins Co.
    - From Douglass Boardman, Trumansburg, to SR, August 13, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      The State Superintendent has asked that each district send in the number and description of the books in the school libraries. Boardman also reports that a district meeting will soon take place to discuss new school sites and taxes.
    - From S. Young, Secretary's Office, Department of Common Schools, Albany to SR, September 4, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      The state regulation calling for a catalogue of books held by each district must be followed.
    - To SR from D. W. Carley, Newfield, September 21, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Carley tells of his plans for the ending of the school term and the examination of his pupils.
    - From S. Town to SR. Town "will come to Ithaca.", October 3, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
    - From E. Powell, Owego, to SR, October 17, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Letter sends news of Teacher Institute.
    - From S. D. Carr, Groton, to SR, October 21, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Letter about the possible hiring of a Mr. Everson in SR's district.
    - From Alex Holland, Union Coll., to SR, December 3, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Acknowledgment payment of money to Union College.
    - From Horace Mann, Boston, to SR, December 31, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 5)
      Can not meet with SR until following April. Commends SR for his (SR's) new work in New York State common schools.
  - January 10 - July 18, 1845 (15 items)
    - From P. A. Ely, Hector, to SR, Superintendent Tompkins Co. Common Schools, January 10, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      A request of SR can not be fulfilled and Ely does not, have a candidate for the Normal School.
    - From Robert Alien, Joseph Ammack, Samuel Alien, Jonathan Owen, Woodard White, and John Fish, all of Enfield, to SR, Superintendent of Tompkins Co. Common Schools, January 15, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Letter is an appeal to SR in behalf of a poor family in the school district. The District Board of Trustees has demanded the payment of the rate bill by this man who does not have the money. The petitioners are asking SR to exempt this man from the rate bill.
    - From S. Town of Aurora to SR, Supt. Tompkins Co. Common School, March 8, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      S. Town can not accept invitation of SR.
    - From E. G. Starke, Auburn, to SR, March 10, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      A letter which SR mailed to Starke had been sent to the wrong address and the event which Starke had been invited to, had already taken place. Starke is angered by a movement in Albany seeking to abolish County Superintendents. He attacks Silas Wright, U.S. Senator 1833; reelected 1837 and 1843; governor 1845-47, as being the American Cato and states that Wright has not the information needed to make the statements he has been making. Starke comes out against "bigotry and ignorance coupled with rank injustice in high stations."
    - From Edwin Cooper, Waterloo Academy, to SR, March 15, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Cooper can not "during his vacation" visit SR but will be in Ithaca for two days during the next institute. He praises SR's work and comments on the effect it has upon other counties.
    - From S. Young, Ballston, to SR, Ithaca, March 25, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      The letter is an answer to an invitation of SR to Young. Young talks about the prejudices of certain segments of the community against the school system. Young says that education is not for the rich alone, as the mass of people think, but for the poor as well. No one should be denied the opportunity of receiving an education. '"No philanthropist should remit his exertions until our Schools are raised to such a grade of utility as to embrace all the children of the State, the sons and daughters of the rich as well as of the poor. All should here mingle on one common level; all should be blended into one mass during the susceptible period of youth. This is the only means of promoting the harmony of society, of suppressing jealousies and perpetuating in letter and in spirit our republican institutions."
    - From Edwin Cooper, Waterloo to SR, Ithaca, April 7, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Cooper will not be able to attend the Teacher Institute in Ithaca because of the illness of his wife.
    - From Cyrus Robertson, Albion, Michigan, to his brother Smith Robertson, Ithaca, May 4, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
    - >Lovel (?) Preston, Caroline, to SR, May 30, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Letter is praising SR for his system of school instruction.
    - Printed folder - written by Franklin Knight, July 1, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      The folder is a sort of advertisement for a book of facsimiles of letter from George Washington on agriculture Knight has published that will "have a most salutary influence in correcting, in the youth of our country, many false notions regarding the character of agricultural pursuits."
    - Letter from the publisher, Alexander V. Blake, N.Y.C. to SR, July 1, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Printed circular for Wickham's "Educational Incentives," particularly Teacher's Tokens with facsimile. Letter tells SR about the invention of a School Ledger which would enable a teacher to keep permanent records of students.
    - From I (?) Cooper McLean, N.Y., to SR, July 2, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      A new certificate is to be made out for Miss Samantha Burton enabling her to teach in any school district in Tompkins' County.
    - R. Hyde Walworth, President, New York Juvenile Temperance Association to SR and all County and town superintendents, July 4, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Printed circular urging them to promote said association and its goals in their district or county.
    - From Francis Dwight, Albany, to SR, July 7, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      A Mr. D. P. Page will be in the area in the middle of September and will be willing to address a Teacher Institute if there is one at that time.
    - From Henry McGonegal of Albany, July 18, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 6)
      Asking SR for a recommendation. McGonegal is seeking a position in Syracuse as a teacher.
  - August 11 - November 13, 1845 (10 items)
    - From Albert D. Wright, Verona to SR, Ithaca, August 11, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Dwight had promised SR that he would speak at the Tompkins County Teachers' Institute. He is asking to be released from this engagement since he is being asked by his own district (county) to be in charge of an Institute there.
    - From E. C. Seymour, Albany, to SR, Ithaca, August 11, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Letter informs that Seymour will be leaving the school at the end of the term. Professors Perkins and Page will not be able to attend the Tompkins County Institute. Seymour asks the help of SR in finding a job for the next term.
    - Circular giving details of the coming Cayuga County Teachers' Institute, August 13, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
    - From Henry Barnard of Providence to SR, Ithaca, September 14, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Barnard will be able to attend the Institute and will deliver an address on "What can be done to improve the schools this winter?"
    - From Henry Barnard,Providence, to SR, Ithaca, October 5, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      The letter confirms Barnard's appearance at the Teachers' Institute, October 14 and announces his plans for an earlier arrival.
    - From Edwin Cooper, Syracuse, to SR, Ithaca, October 22, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Cooper will not be able to attend the Teachers' Institute. He also encourages SR to accept a copy of a "current volume of the Advocates'" and to encourage the teachers in his district to become subscribers.
    - From O. O. Wickham, N.Y.C. to SR, October 27, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Wickham will not be able to attend the Institute and present his "Educational Incentives" to the teachers present. However, he is sending samples and asks that a wall chart called School Chart of Characteristics be placed on the wall of some room at the Institute.
    - From Charles R. Coburn, Owego, to SR, October 30, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Inviting SR and Mr. Barnard to the Owego Institute and Esq. Gillet, if he can be spared. He invites SR to speak to them about education.
    - From Daniel Jackson, Burdett, to SR, November 8, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      About a teacher, Mr. J. W. Carpenter, then teaching at his school, who had the previous year been in trouble over a young woman of the town whom he had since married. Jackson says that except for that one incident, Carpenter's reputation and behavior had been very fine.
    - From O. O. Wickham, N.Y.C. to SR, November 13, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 7)
      Asking for the names of all of those present at the last Teachers' Institute so that he may advertise his Teacher's Book of Instrumentalities and School Requisites.
  - January 27 - July 28, 1846 (12 items)
    - From Thomas Slater, Albany, to SR, January 27, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      Professor Perkins will be able to attend the Institute planned for the spring.
    - From H. Camp, school trustee in Trumansburg, to SR, Supt. of Common Schools, Tompkins County, February 17, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      In regard to a notice that there will be a public examination of students in the near future. Camp says, on behalf of the other trustees, that their school will not be taking part in the examination.
    - From C. S. Ford, Geneva to SR, March 19, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      About Ford's appearance as a lecturer at a future Teachers' Institute.
    - From S. Town, Aurora to SR, March 26, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      Town cannot, at the time, indicate whether or not he will be able to visit Ithaca.
    - From G. H. Stevens, Danby, to SR, April 8, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      Sherman Miller has been newly elected Town Superintendent of Schools. Canfield and Stevens are going to School [to keep school?]
    - From Doug(lass) (Boardman) Trumansburg, to SR as Superintendent of Common Schools, Tompkins Co, May 20, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      Giving exact time of his arrival in Ithaca.
    - SR from T. Russell Jencks of Boston, May 26, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
    - From Palmer and Jencks, Boston, to SR, Supt. of Common Schools, June 15, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      They have found the journals he enquired about and wish to know if he wants them to be sent to him.
    - Printed circular from N. S. Benton, Supt., N.Y.S., Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, July 1, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      A previous circular should be disregarded if it does not apply to a particular Superintendent,.
    - From J. S. (or I. S.) Mitchell, Canajoharie, to SR, July 10, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
    - From Superintendent of Caroline to SR, July 28, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 8)
      Reporting on the salary of the County and town superintendent of schools note attached re: amount of compensation for Dr. Farlin [See Ace. #2241]. Town Superintendent.
  - August 12 - October 26, 1846 (11 items)
    - From Jacob Abbott of New York to SR, August 12, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)